A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Affairs Division, Program Staff Files FA548
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Affairs Division, Program Staff Files
1956-1990, bulk 1964-1983
1964-1983
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA548
3.04 Cubic Feet 8 letter document boxes
The International Affairs Program Staff Files collection was created by combining inactive records from the International Affairs Program (USIAP), the International Division, the Developing Countries Program Office for Latin America and the Caribbean (OLAC), and International Training and Research (ITR). The collection documents various periods in the history of these programs from 1956 to 1990 and is organized into five series: International Affairs Chronological Files (1990), Middle East and Africa (MEA) Field Office Files (1964-1969), International Training and Research Files (1956-1971), International Training Evaluation (1969-1983), and Program Planning Budgets (1962-1983). MEA Field Office Files include staff directories, post reports, and memoranda concerning financial reporting and evaluation procedures, family maintenance on travel and study awards, and the development of a new accounting system. International Training and Research files document the Foundation's involvement with the development of international academic exchange and study abroad programs during the 1960s. The files contain correspondence, memoranda, reports, papers, and background information about a wide variety of topics, including the problems universities face with the acquisition and bibliographic control of foreign research materials, the Foundation's policy for language development, and Foundation support for ESL, Russian and East European Studies, and international legal studies. The International Training Evaluation files consists of Robert G. Myer's research files for his 1982-1983 study of Ford Foundation support between 1960 and 1980 for post-graduate education abroad for Third World nationals. The files include the raw data and background research that Dr. Myers compiled over the course of his evaluation as well as drafts and comments on his report.
Biographical / Historical
Robert G. Myers was born September 2, 1934. He received a B.A. in Economics from Oberlin College in 1955, a M.A. in Education from Stanford University in 1962, and was awarded a PhD in Comparative Education by the University of Chicago in 1967. He joined the Ford Foundation in August 1972 as a Program Officer in the Office for Latin America and the Caribbean (OLAC/LAC). In November of 1976, he became a Project Specialist to the Office of the Vice President and was seconded to the International Development Research Centre in Ottawa, Canada. He returned in July of 1979, and he was made Program Adviser for the Andean Region and the Southern Cone. Throughout his time at the Foundation, his work primarily focused on education and development projects in Latin America. In 1982, he embarked on a 15-month evaluation of the Foundation's support for international training programs for Third World nationals between 1960 and 1980. The evaluative study was intended to create a framework for acting on renewed interest in foreign training among granting institutions on individual, institutional and national levels, despite an environment of reduced budgets.
His work entailed conducting interviews and country case studies, primarily of Indonesia and Peru, and collecting data about support for education from the Foundation's various offices. The study was intended to address such questions as the variation and effect of different strategies adopted by the Foundation, approaches to selection and placement, administration and cost, rates of successful completion and return home, and impact of training on individuals and institutions. Dr. Myers left the Foundation on August 15, 1983.
Melvin J. Fox was born on November 26, 1913 and graduated from American University in 1940 with a B.A. in International Economics. He joined the Ford Foundation in July 1951 as a consultant on international affairs as part of its charter staff. In November of the same year he became a staff associate and, in 1953, he advanced to Executive Associate for International Training and Research (ITR). Mr. Fox was promoted to Program Associate in October of 1957 and he served as Associate Director of the International Training and Research Program from 1961 through 1966. In early 1967, he became Program Officer for Planning and Evaluation in the International Division, and later that year was promoted to Deputy Representative for West Africa within the Middle East and Africa (MEA) Program. Mr. Fox subsequently held the positions of Program Officer for the Middle East and Africa (1970) and Program Advisor for MEA (1972) before rising to Representative for West Africa in May 1975. From September 5 to November 2, 1983, he was Acting Representative for the Developing Countries Program in Lagos, Nigeria. During his time at Ford, his work focused on foreign academic exchange, the teaching of English abroad, development projects in Africa, and African studies at U.S. Universities. Mr. Fox died in 1998.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation has been engaged in overseas work since the early 1950s. This work was driven by the Foundation's aspiration to become a national and international philanthropy for the advancement of human welfare, first formally expressed in the seminal 1949 Gaither Study Committee report commissioned by the Board of Trustees to chart the institution's future. In 1951, the Foundation established two of its first grant programs, Overseas Development (OD) and Overseas Training and Research (OTR). The granting goals were to increase agricultural production, improve health and living conditions, and advance education. South and Southeast Asia was the initial focus, with India and Pakistan receiving the majority of grants. A more limited number of grants were issued in Indonesia and Burma. A program for smaller regional and national grants also was initiated for the Near East. In 1957, Overseas Development further expanded to include programs in Latin America.
In 1957, the Foundation established a program in International Training and Research (ITR) aimed at strengthening American competence in foreign affairs and international relations. ITR supported scholarship and teaching in areas in which American knowledge and trained personnel were limited. The Foundation offered area studies in Asia, Africa, the Near East, the Soviet Union, and East Europe. In its international training and exchange programs, the Foundation and its grantees coordinated closely with the U.S. State Department. This cooperation was required by the United States Information and Educational Exchange Act of 1948 (Public Law 80-402 or Smith–Mundt Act), which sponsored exchanges between the United States and other countries as a matter of government policy.
As part of a Foundation reorganization in 1966, the Overseas Development Program, along with other international programs such as ITR and Population, became part of a single International Division (ID). A subsequent restructuring of the International Division occurred in 1980-1981 and led to the creation of the Developing Countries Program (DCP). DCP was again restructured in 1989, resulting in the breaking out of programs in Africa and the Middle East (AME), Asia (ASIA), Latin American and the Caribbean (LAC/OLAC), Human Rights and Governance (HRG), Education and Culture (EC), Program-Related Investments (PRI), and International Affairs (IA) as independent program areas.
The International Affairs program focused on combating problems of a global scale, including environmental degradation, massive refugee movements, population pressures, inter-ethnic and communal violence, narcotics trafficking, and terrorism. Believing that important issues of worldwide concern should be addressed collectively by analysts and policy makers from multiple nations, the Foundation developed independent multilateral institutions and employed International Affairs specialists in the U.S. and abroad to promote the rule of public international law. This led to Foundation support for research, public education, and advanced training in seven broad areas, including international peace, security and arms control; international economics and development; contemporary international studies, primarily of the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe; and the processes and substance of U.S. foreign policy.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into 5 series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series I. International Affairs (IA) Chronological Files, 1990
Series II. International Division/Middle East and Africa (ID/MEA) Field Office Files, 1964-1969
Series III. International Training and Research (ITR) Files, 1956-1967
Series IV. International Training Evaluation, 1969-1983
Series V. Program Planning Budgets, 1962-1983
Scope and Contents
The International Affairs Program Staff Files consist of an artificially created collection of records from International Affairs (IA), the International Division (ID), the Developing Countries Program (DCP), and International Training and Research (ITR) documenting various periods in the history of these programs from 1956 to 1990.
The most recent files, dating from April to December 1990, consist of correspondence and memoranda collected weekly from IA staff. The files contain memoranda written about various topics, including the Foundation's International Research Competition on Global and Regional Approaches to Conventional Arms Control and International Peacekeeping, and support for training in public international law through exchange of students and scholars between the U.S. and selected institutions in developing countries. Other topics include the Soviet and Eastern Europe Study Group (SEESG) and the Women's International Forum at the United Nations. Memoranda also report and comment on the Delegated-Authority Project (DAP) and Foundation-Administered Project (FAP) grant actions, grant proposals, grantee/project evaluations, monitoring visits, telephone conversations, and meetings and conferences attended by IA program officers.
Files from the International Division include files for field offices in the Middle East and Africa (MEA) dating from the 1960s, and program planning budgets (also called proposed budget books) for fiscal years spanning from 1963 to 1985. The MEA files contain staff directories and post reports with information about living conditions and Ford Foundation policy for overseas personnel. Memoranda in the files concern a range of topics, including financial reporting and evaluation procedures, family maintenance on travel and study awards and the development of a new accounting system.
Files pertaining to the International Training and Research (ITR) Program appear to be subject files maintained by Melvin J. Fox during his tenure as ITR Associate Director (1961-1966). Several files describe the Foundation's involvement in the development of international academic exchange and study abroad programs during the 1960s. The records concern the problems universities face with the acquisition and bibliographic control of foreign research materials, a meeting with President Lyndon B. Johnson's educational advisors regarding the International Education Act of 1966. The files also contain studies by foreign students and U.S. academic professionals abroad. Also discussed are the Foundation's policy for language development and its support for ESL, Russian and East European Studies, and international legal studies programs.
The Developing Countries Program files consist of the research files kept by Robert G. Myers, a Program Officer and Program Advisor for the Office for Latin America and the Caribbean. From 1982 to 1983, Dr. Myers undertook an International Training Evaluation which studied the Foundation's support for post-graduate education of Third World Nationals from 1960 to 1980. The files include raw data and background research that Dr. Myers compiled over the course of his evaluation, as well as drafts and comments on his report.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Related Materials
FA582 Ford Foundation records, Office of Humanities and the Arts, Office of the Vice President, Office Files of Wilson McNeil Lowry. Spanning from 1952 to 1974 this collection contains files relating to the International Affairs, Overseas Development, and International Training and Research programs in the 1960s. These programs were under Mr. Lowry's oversight.
FA619 Ford Foundation records, International Affairs, Office Files of Joseph E. Slater. This collection, spanning from 1957 to 1967, consists of files relating to such topics as the Atlantic partnership, European community, economic development, developing countries, east-west relations, Asia and the Pacific, science and technology, and international affairs education. Slater held various positions within the International Affairs Program between 1957 and 1967, including serving as Program Officer in Charge from January to November 1967.
FA528 Ford Foundation records, Developing Countries Program, Program Staff Files. These files relate to the work of the International Division (later the Developing Countries Program) in Latin America and Asia and consist mainly of correspondence concerning administrative matters and budget reports. The collection spans from 1973 to 1987.
FA624 Ford Foundation records, Office of the Vice President, Office Files of David Bell. This collection holds the office files of the Vice President (1966-1969) and Executive Vice President (1969-1981) of the International Division.
Ford Foundation administrative manuals and post reports, 1953-1973. This collection consists of administrative publications and post reports relating to Ford Foundation offices in New York, Asia and the Pacific, Latin America, and the Middle East and Africa. The administrative manuals offer standard procedures on office administration and personnel issues. Post reports provide advice, tips, and information about health, education and living conditions in overseas countries for Ford Foundation personnel and their families going abroad.
- International Affairs (IA) Chronological Files, 1990; I; 1.14 Cubic Feet 3 letter document boxes
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of memoranda originating and collected weekly from International Affairs (IA) staff from April to December 1990. Subjects covered in the memoranda include comment s about of IA and Foundation policy such as external affirmative action and IA priorities for the use of worldwide funds, and special grant making procedures for Japan. Also reviewed are IA programs such as the International Research Competition on Global and Regional Approaches to Conventional Arms Control and International Peacekeeping, and Foundation support for training in public international law through exchange of students between the U.S. and developing countries. International Affairs Division and other Foundation staff members who authored memoranda include Enid C. B. Schoettle, Stanley J. Heginbotham, Paul Balaran, Mary McClymont, Karel Vosskuhler, Susan Berresford, Craufurd Goodwin, Laurice Sarraf, Brian Urquhart, and Seamus O'Cleireacain.
  Arrangement
  Chronological
  - Chronological Files, 1990, April 2-13 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, 1990, April 16-27 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files, 1990, April 30-May 4 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files, 1990, May 7-11 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files, 1990, May 14-23 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files, 1990, May 22-31 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files, 1990, June 1-6 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chronological Files, 1990, June 12-20 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chronological Files, 1990, June 18-26 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, 1990 June 24-July 5 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files, 1990 July 2-13 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files, 1990 July 9-27 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files, 1990 July 25-August 3 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files, 1990 August 2-31 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files, 1990 September (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Chronological Files, 1990 October (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Chronological Files, 1990 November (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Chronological Files, 1990 December (Box 3, Folder 1)
- International Division / Middle East and Africa (ID/MEA) Field Office Files, 1964-1969; II; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
  This series consists of field office files kept by the International Division's Office for the Middle East and Africa (MEA). The files are arranged alphabetically by originating field offices within MEA, including Ankara (Turkey), Beirut (Lebanon), Cairo (Egypt, formally United Arab Republic), Lagos (Nigeria), New York, and Tunis (Tunisia). The files contain staff directories and post reports. There are also memoranda on financial reporting and evaluation procedures, family maintenance on travel and study awards, and the development of a new accounting system.
  - FF Ankara Office -- Information on FF Policy on Housing, Automobiles, Banking, etc. in Turkey, Memoranda Re: Special Paragraphs for Grant Letters to Turkish Grantees, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - FF Ankara Office -- Memoranda Re: Routing of New York Memos to the Field, Change of Address for Ankara Office, etc., 1966 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - FF Ankara Office -- News of the Week Concerning Ankara Office Sent to Eugene P. Northrop, 1965 December 3 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - FF Beirut Office -- Memoranda Re: Beirut Office Program Status and Personnel, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - FF Beirut Office -- Memoranda Re: Quarterly Grant Payment Procedures, Administration of Fellowship Funds, Press Announcement of Overseas Development Grants, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - FF Beirut Office -- Summary Notes of International Division Meeting in Beirut, List of Staff in Beirut, Memoranda Re: Stopover Visit from George F. Gant, etc., 1967 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - FF Cairo, U.A.R. Office -- Cairo Staff Directory, Memoranda Re: Report on Inter-African Public Administration Seminar, etc., 1966-1969 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - FF Lagos Office -- Memoranda Re: Grant Recommendation Procedures, West Africa Grant Actions, etc., 1965-1968 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - FF New York Office -- Memoranda Re: MEA Dependent Organizations, Financial Reporting and Evaluation Procedures for MEA Office, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - FF Tunis Office -- Memorandum Re: Quarterly Forecast, Algerian English Language Training Project, Tunisian Library Development Project, etc., 1967 January 23 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- International Training and Research (ITR) Files, 1956-1967; III; 0.76 Cubic Feet 2 letter document boxes
  This series consists of subject files documenting the work of the Foundation's International Training and Research (ITR) program. Melvin J. Fox, who was serving as ITR Associate Director (1961-1966) appears to have collected the files. They contain correspondence, memoranda, reports, papers, and background information about a wide variety of topics, including the Foundation's policy for language development, problems associated with the acquisition and bibliographic control of foreign research materials by university libraries, and studies of the transitional challenges faced by foreign students as well as U.S. academic professionals abroad.
  - "Education for the Public Service: A Survey" (report), 1961 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - English Language Development -- Memoranda and Reports on FF and U.S. Government Programs in ESL in Middle East, Africa, Southeast Asia, etc. (1 of 2), 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - English Language Development -- Memoranda and Reports on FF Activities in Teaching ESL, Meetings of Inter-Program Committee on English as a Second Language (2 of 2), 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Ford Foundation Policy -- International Training and Research (ITR), Comments on Memorandum Re: Staff Communications with Prospective Grantees, 1965 June 25 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Foreign Students -- Background Paper on Organizations Concerned with Foreign Students for Meeting on Institute of International Education Renewal Request, 1965 June (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - International Academic Exchange -- Correspondence Re: Transition Seminar for Foreign Students, Conference on "The European-American Scholarly Community," etc., 1966 October (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - International Education Act of 1966 -- Background, Correspondence Re: Meeting with President Johnson's Educational Advisors, etc., 1966 February-1967 January (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - International Legal Studies Programs -- List of FF Grantees/Grants, 1964 December 1 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - International Library Resources -- Correspondence and Background on Problems Universities Face with Acquisition and Bibliographic Control of Foreign Research Materials (1 of 2), 1964-1966 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - International Library Resources -- Correspondence and Background on Problems Universities Face with Acquisition and Bibliographic Control of Foreign Research Materials (2 of 2), 1966 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Latin American Language Problems -- Memoranda and Correspondence Re: Teaching Language and Linguistics, Background, 1956-1966 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - OIR Self-Study on European/Atlantic Studies -- Correspondence Re: Conversations with Harvard Professors Stanley Hoffman, Henry Kissinger, et al on FF Role in Europe and European Studies, etc., 1967 October-November (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Research on Professional Practices Overseas -- Correspondence, Papers and Speech on U.S. Academic Professionals Overseas, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Russian and East European Studies -- List of FF Grants to Universities, 1966 December (Box 4, Folder 6)
- International Training Evaluation, 1969-1983; IV; 1.14 Cubic Feet 3 letter document boxes
  This series consists of Robert G. Myer's research files for his 1982-1983 study of Ford Foundation support between 1960 and 1980 for post-graduate education abroad for Third World nationals. Included in the series are grant and working files containing Myer's pre-proposal, project description, progress report, final report outline, summary conclusions with comments, guiding questions, references, and interview notes. Background information, reports, and questionnaires from evaluative studies conducted by other institutions of their study abroad programs such as the Institute for International Education (IIE), the Rockefeller Foundation, the Inter-American Foundation, and the African-American Institute also are included. In addition, the files contain raw data, including human resources inventories for Argentina, Brazil, Chile, Colombia, Mexico, Peru, and the broader region of Latin America. The inventories contain information about the recipients of graduate fellowships, field of study and current career placement. The inventories were used as a resource to identify possible consultants.
  - African-American Institute -- Study of Former AFGRAD Fellows Questionnaire, Notes, Background, circa 1983 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Agency for International Development (USAID) -- Background on AID Support for Training and Exchange Programs in Latin America, Participant Training Costs, 1975-1981 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Agricultural Economics -- Notes on FF Support for Rural Social Sciences in Latin America, Background on Training Agricultural Economists for International Development Work, etc., 1980-1983 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Economics -- Background Evaluation and Research Proposal to Study Performance of Foreign Students by the Economics Institute, 1974-1976 (Box 4, Folder 10)